<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The answer of His Excellencie Sir Thomas Fairfax, (in behalf of the whole Army) to the votes and desires of both Houses of Parliament, concerning the resigning up of His Majesties royall person. Wherein he declares, I. The reasons of his advance nearer to the City of London. II. The Armies resolution to secure the Kings person. III. Their charging of a party within the city, for raising a new army (against them, as they suppose) which should rendevous near the city of Worcester. IV. And lastly, the Armies protestation towards the citizens of London; with their propositions, concerning the bringing of His royall Majestie to Whitehall. Sent from the Army by the commissioners, Iune 23.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2334A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E393_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201602</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862102</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862102</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160310</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88304)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160310)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E393[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The answer of His Excellencie Sir Thomas Fairfax, (in behalf of the whole Army) to the votes and desires of both Houses of Parliament, concerning the resigning up of His Majesties royall person. Wherein he declares, I. The reasons of his advance nearer to the City of London. II. The Armies resolution to secure the Kings person. III. Their charging of a party within the city, for raising a new army (against them, as they suppose) which should rendevous near the city of Worcester. IV. And lastly, the Armies protestation towards the citizens of London; with their propositions, concerning the bringing of His royall Majestie to Whitehall. Sent from the Army by the commissioners, Iune 23.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
                  <author>Linfield, E.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Williamson.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: St. Albanes June 23. 1647. E. Linfield.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, --  Baron, 1612-1671 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160310:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
            <p>THE ANSWER Of His Excellencie S<hi rend="sup">ir</hi> THOMAS FAIRFAX, <hi>(in behalf of the whole Army)</hi> TO THE VOTES and DESIRES of Both Houſes OF PARLIAMENT, Concerning the reſigning up of His Majeſties Royall Perſon.</p>
            <p>Wherein he Declares,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <label>I.</label> 
                     <hi>The Reaſons of His advance nearer to the City of</hi> London.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>II.</label> 
                     <hi>The Armies Reſolution to ſecure the Kings Perſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>III.</label> 
                     <hi>Their charging of a party within the City, for raiſing a new Army (againſt them, as they ſuppoſe) which ſhould rendevous near the City of</hi> Worceſter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>IV.</label> 
                     <hi>And laſtly, The Armies Proteſtation towards the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of London; With their Propoſitions, concerning the bringing of His Royall Majeſtie to</hi> Whitehall.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Sent from the Army by the Commiſſioners, <hi>Iune</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Williamſon.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:160310:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:160310:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>SEVERALL HEADS OF THE DECLARATION, <hi>Sent from the Army by the Commiſſioners, on Wedneſday the</hi> 23. <hi>of June,</hi> 1647.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kinde Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving by your laſt Letter, dated the 22. of this inſtant, received ſeverall papers incloſed therein, touching your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent proceedings at <hi>London;</hi> all which I have ſeriouſly peruſed, and do render you many thanks for the ſame. And becauſe I am loth
<pb facs="tcp:160310:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->to ſhew my ſelf too much ungratefull, and leave you unſatisfied in your preſent expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, I ſhall here, as briefly as poſſibly I can, repreſent unto you ſome ſmall collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which I have lately drawn up, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the great and grand Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Army, aſſented to by the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and ſouldiers under command of His Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and ſent up to London by the Commiſſioners, June 23 to bee communicated to the Honourable Houſes of Parliament aſſembled at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, and the Lord Major and Court of Aldermen of the City of London.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is declared,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the gallant expreſſions of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in the ſaid Declaration, ſhewing the Reaſons of their neerer approach towards the City of <hi>London,</hi> and that the Army hath voted (with one unanimous conſent) to have the Kings Majeſty conducted with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſafety to <hi>Richmond,</hi> together with the Commiſſioners, and the reſt of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants about the King; but hath declared againſt thoſe perſons, expreſſed in the Votes
<pb facs="tcp:160310:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->of both houſes of Parliament, for guarding of his Majeſties perſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that having been lately infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of a malignant party within the City, whoſe indeavours tended only for the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of diſcord, caſting falſe ſuggeſtions and aſperſions upon the Army, and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make them odious to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that being ſenſible of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of the aforeſaid party, and having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly diſcovered their private actions for contriving of a new war againſt this Army, who (by the Power of <hi>Heaven</hi>) hath beene the chiefe and inſtrumentall meanes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering the people of <hi>England</hi> from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall flavery; therefore, for the prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all conſpiracies and dangers that may ariſe, tending to the prejudice of the Peace of this Kingdome, it is declared in the name of the whole army, that they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend or yeeld to the votes of both Houſes of Parliament, touching the Guard expreſſed therein, but ſhall with all faithfulneſſe and diligence endeavour to preſerve his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb facs="tcp:160310:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->Royall perſon from danger, and to that end hath appointed a competent number of faithfull, zealous, and religious men, choſe out of ſeverall Regiments in the army, to guard and ſecure his Majeſties perſon at his Court at <hi>Richmond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that the army is ſenſible of the great malice and inveteracy of divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt them, who indeavour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve and embroyle this Nation in a new war, by which means, if once effected, would prove prejudiciall and deſtructive to the fundamental Lawes of this Kingdom, &amp; the liberty and propriety of the Subject.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, that they have bin very active in ſeveral parts of the Kingdom, to raiſe forces and to that end hath endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe themſelves of divers ſtrong Holds, throughout this Realm; as alſo their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to raiſe a diviſion in the army, and to withdraw the hearts of the ſouldiers from the Officers, which indeed is a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for thouſands to do, their hearts being ſo firmly knit and united together.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, that ſo ſoon as they could have
<pb facs="tcp:160310:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->accompliſhed their wicked deſign, for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of an Army on foot, their intents were to randezvouz near the City of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, they further deſire that the Kings Majeſty may be reſtored to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Rights, and tryumphantly brought to his Royal Palace at White-hall.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they profeſſe and declare to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tizens of <hi>London,</hi> that they have no evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent againſt them, neither will they injure any, either by ſtopping of proviſion, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of traffique, unleſſe ehey be forced &amp; conſtrained thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All which fore going Reaſons are declared to be the chiefe cauſe of the Armies neare approach towards the City of London</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dizers other particulars were propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That they have not received a ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory anſwer, touching their former Papers and Repreſentations, humbly propoſed to the honourable Pouſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Juſtice may be executed, and a legall tryall appointed for the Eleven Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which now ſtands charged by the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:160310:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <p>And thirdly, touching ſome ſouldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Sir <hi>Robert Pyes</hi> Regiment.</p>
            <p>Divers Regiments of the army are upon their march towards <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> and ſo either to <hi>Kingſton</hi> or <hi>Windſor</hi> for a Head-quarter. God grant a happy concluſion of <hi>Englands</hi> diſtractions, and a good correſpondency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Parliament, City, and army, that ſo Peace and truth may flouriſh within his Maieſties Realms and Dominions, which is the earneſt deſire of him, who remaines</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, to ſerve you, <hi>E. LINFIELD</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>St. <hi>Albanes</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 23. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
